Inventory of the Samuel Newell Watson papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Samuel Newell Watson papers
1910-1918
XX033
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 13 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (22.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, photographs, and postcards relating to relief work in France during World War I and to the Allied Powers during the war.
Watson, Samuel Newell, 1861-1942.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Reverend Doctor Samuel Newell Watson was born on February 27, 1861. He married Jeannette Watkins in January 1885. Watson was the acting rector for the Episcopal American Church of the Holy Trinity in Paris, France from 1912 to 1918. Additionally, he was vice president of the American Executive Committee for Fatherless Children of France and vice president of the American Ambulance Hospital in France. Following World War I, he became a Knight of the Legion of Honor of France and of the Legion of Honor of Belgium.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Samuel Newell Watson are composed of correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, photographs, and postcards relating to relief work in France during World War I, specifically by the American Church of the Holy Trinity, and to the Allied Powers during the war.
Americans--France.; International relief.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care.
- Belgian Soldier's Songbook, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Proclamation of safeguard, circa 1910 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- 33rd Division American Expeditionary Forces, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- La Veillée des Armes, 1915 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- American Ambassador's Fund receipt, 1914 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Photographs, circa 1910 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Het Toppunt der Beschaving (The Pinnacle of Civilization), circa 1914
  Scope and Contents note
  Artwork by Louis Raemaekers created in response to World War I.
  - Het Toppunt der Beschaving (Box-folder 2; 1)
  - Tweede Serie (Series 2) (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Derder Serie (Series 3) (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Vierde Serie (Series 4) (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Vijfde Serie (Series 5) (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Zesde Serie (Series 6) (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Relief work in Belgium, circa 1914 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  An account of how Samuel Newell Watson was able to assist a small Belgian town during the war.
- Relief work in France, circa 1914 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  Printed matter, including correspondence and a map pertaining to relief efforts in France.
- Posters, circa 1914 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  French posters, including a variety of posters pertaining to the Journée nationale des orphelins (National Day of the Orphans). Please use included photocopies of the posters to facilitate access. Originals housed in oversize folder.
- Scrapbooks, 1914 August 1
  Scrapbooks kept by Jeanette Grace Watson, the wife of Samuel Newell Watson. Includes correspondence, photographs, maps, printed matter, and information on services rendered by the American Church of the Holy Trinity. Blank pages were removed from scrapbooks in May 2016.
  - Salutation (Box 3)
  - We with America (Boxes 4-6)
  - We with the American Red Cross (Box 7)
  - We with Belgium (Box 8)
  - We with England (Box 9)
  - We with France (Boxes 10-11)
  - We with the Fatherless Children (Box 12)
  - We with Russia, Italy and Romania (Box 13)
  - We with Serbia (Box 14)